Hi, it's Mike again with Nuke-tastic. I'm here today again at the GoToChicago conference, GoToChicago 2013. I'm sitting down with Mike Miller, who is the founder and chief scientist of Cloudens. And they're a database as a service company. Their specialty is CouchDB and BigCouch. So thank you very much for taking the time to sit down Mike. Thanks for the chance. Okay, the CouchDB, how did Cloudens get to be involved with the CouchDB project?
Very good question. Is it okay if I just back up a little bit and give you kind of one overall kind of mission statement, like a theme for the company? Absolutely.
Yeah.
So we started the company because our backgrounds are in big science and big data from Large Hadron Collider and CERN. A lot. So some of the biggest data sets in the world. Some big data. Yeah, we got the feeling that big data was going to be a thing.
Right.
And that if it was a problem for us, it was eventually going to be a problem for everybody. I think that's been borne out. But the other thing we learned over the last four years since we did Y Combinator is that mobile is also a big thing. And so I think these, I think the founder of Joint put it best that mobile and big data have broken our model of computing.
So that's what Cloudens is trying to solve. And so we're trying to build a CDN for your database. And so we run that as, as a service. And if you step back and say of all the APIs and systems out there that can really deal with big as well as disconnected, you know, that takes you directly and only to CouchDB. So that's how we got integrated with the projects. And so we've brought a lot of IP to that project, both internally and in the open source.
Okay.
And that's really the API layer that we're using, you know, for this big vision of solving those two problems.
But why Couch?
And even one more question is, is, were you part of the creation of CouchDB or was it something more you saw and you adopted?
Yeah.
So Cloudens has been involved from a pretty early stage. But we, you know, we became friends of the CouchDB community in late 2008.
Okay.
And I think we've been big supporters since. We have a large number of committers actually to the project. I think maybe over half of the committers are actually on the cloud and payroll. It's a big part of their job. But if you step back just technically, you know, we're not necessarily the CouchDB company. The things we love about it are its data model that's really built uniquely from the ground up so that you can have like two disconnected systems. Like one can be my phone and one can be the cloud.
Right.
That have a database and have a document with the same name, right, or the same ID.
They can be like, they can be causally disconnected initially, but they can be synchronized at a later point in time.
Okay.
Which is, I think, what mobile really requires. And then the other thing is just Couch is it's pretty radical from the API standpoint if you're used to using a relational database.
Right. Yeah.
It's a very different. It's totally different.
Right.
Approach. But I think it's very forward thinking in the sense that, okay, the internet happened.
People use JSON. And, you know, everything speaks HTTP.
Well, briefly, could you just kind of describe why Couch is different?
So if somebody's watching and they haven't used Couch at all, a little, maybe comparing, they probably know Mongo because that's really famous.
Sure. But Couch, what, how is it different than Mongo?
So I think it's, it's, um, I've got a couple answers to that. Um, I think number one is that it's a document database and I think it's maybe the first document database. I think it really coined that phrase.
Okay.
Um, and it's been a pure cloud. Um, there's not a company that started and then built it and released it.
Right.
Um, so I, I often compare, you know, Mongo and CouchDB as like MySQL and Postgres.
Okay.
Like CouchDB community is slow. It's deliberate. Um, and it's in it, you know, for the decades.
Right. Right.
It's not necessarily like gotta get to market right now.
Yeah.
Um, and that defines the culture and the product path a lot. Um, but from the API standpoint, it's very different, right, than a typical database. Um, just from the way you talk to it, it's your database is a web server, um, which is pretty radical if you worked in like big enterprise.
Right. Right.
Like usually lock down the database. In this case, it's like, well, you know, the internet has taught us how to build very secure and high availability, you know, systems. So let's just boil, bake that into the database itself and think about, you know, working towards a goal of eliminating the middle tier if you want to and just let the database do a lot of the things that you generally need. Well, one, well, one thing that I think when somebody first looks at couch though, I, as somebody who's come fresh to it myself, uh, that you don't write queries in the same way, that it's more queries up front and then you start pushing data into the queries than defining a schema or just pushing raw data into, uh, I think. Yeah, it's different. Um, it, so the thing about a document database is the idea that, uh, in contrast, like, uh, column stores, like Cassandra H base or big table, um, it's not schematized.
Right.
So you don't have to sit down and pre declare what you're going to put in and be limited in how you can query that later on downstream in your project. With the document database, the idea is you can always build a new index to do what you need to.
Um, so that's step number one. Um, but step number two is couch DB is very much from the ground up built to be stable in production. And so things like table scans don't really exist.
Right.
Because they're neat when you're starting a project, but in production they suck.
Yeah. Right?
They're the things that make your site go offline. Um, and so it's very much about, um, recognizing that disk is cheap. So let's store your data durably. Let's make sure it's always flushed to disk with an F-sync before we succeed a response. Um, let's make sure that you can pre-compute, um, that data using that incremental indexing engine, which is very unique. So that no matter how the data is, like stored, it's prepared in exactly the way your application wants to consume it.
Right.
To load a page, drive an app, leaderboard, like you name it. And then, um, the third thing is, I think it's, and this is where it really differs from all other databases, right? Traditionally, databases are like single cursor and you make that cursor really fast because the database may be running on the exact same server that the application is, right?
Right. So it's like, oh, can we beep microseconds? Can we get to nanoseconds?
And that's awesome. But when you're talking to it from your phone, that's a total waste. And what you really want is concurrency. So the, the, the CouchDB philosophy, and this is supported in all the different back ends that implement the API, like whether it's Cloudint or like PouchDB running in your browser, is like all the things you need to load a page in your app, throw them at the database at the same time and deal with those in Ajax fashion, right? Asynchronously as they come back.
Okay.
And so it's like, oh, as long as each of those succeeds in, you know, order 10 milliseconds, you know, Cloudint we try to do single millisecond.
Yeah.
Um, then you're fine. Um, and you can, you know, be well under that hundred milliseconds, um, kind of human tolerance for latency.
Okay.
Um, so it's a very different philosophy than single cursor. So I'm really curious about how, so you're, you earlier, you alluded to that the Cloudint employees are committing to the CouchDB project. It isn't a fork. You didn't fork off, uh, the CouchDB and now this is the Cloudint specific, you know, branded and we're going to add some proprietary things. No, you're contributing into the community project. Yeah, I can, I can try to be a little more precise with that. Um, so we've adopted certain portions of CouchDB in our stack. Um, we've taken the API layer, um, and 95% of it, there are certain things we've turned off that we think are unstable in production at scale. So we, we try to make sure that people can go from megabytes to petabytes, right, without surprises, which is a pretty big challenge. Yeah, yeah, it's a big challenge. Um, and we love the, um, persistency, uh, model. Um, so the engine that actually stores data, this unique append-only B+ tree is fantastic because you never lose data. Like, let's say, we take our systems down with the kill-9.
There's no graceful shutdown. Yeah, yeah, there's just, right. Because it's always consistent. There's no right ahead log. So we love that. The stuff in the middle, um, you know, CouchDB, um, in its current state is a single server application. You can do replicas, you know. Um, so with CloudNum, we brought, um, RIP, which is like, um, predominantly inspired by Dynamo, the original Amazon paper. So like Cassandra, like what you find in Reoc, it is masterless, it's symmetric, no single point of failure. So we put that in between the API and the persistency level. Um, and that's, you know, what we run in our service. So with CloudNum, we'll take a single machine, then we'll turn that into a three-node, you know, a single CouchDB machine can turn into a three-node cluster where we store your data redundantly. Then we just add nodes to that. And our biggest cluster is like 250 nodes right now. So it just scales as you need it to, and it's very graceful. So you have a CloudNum build. Yep. But, but, but, but, but how does that work with the true patches back to Couch for what you, what, hey, this is really good. This is a bug fix. This is going to benefit everybody and ourselves. So that's what we did, that's what we did initially.
Okay.
And then, um, so we've had kind of our code base and the CouchDB code base. And, uh, we've been contributing thing, you know, cherry picking what we can, contributing back, and actually all the time trying to, um, help foster CouchDB to hopefully grow in a direction where it'd be ready to be like a fully clustered service.
Right.
Um, and so I think it was about two years ago, then we said, okay, the code bases are now close enough, right, that we could, um, make a fork of CouchDB.
Okay.
Put our clustering technology back into it with a path of getting that ultimately back into CouchDB.
So that was Big Couch. Um, and, and that was great. That solved the need for people who were running CouchDB themselves, um, and wanted to, and wanted to be able to, you know, scale beyond, you know, replica sets. Um, and now actually just, I think, a month ago, um, we got to the point where the code bases were close enough that we could then take a lot more of what we had, um, beyond even just Big Couch.
Right.
Everything from, like, how we do compaction with multiple file schemes, you know, um, auto-indexing, uh, and quite a big chunk of our IP.
Right. Right.
As, as our, um, uh, as our board pointed out, and put that back into a branch of CouchDB. So Big Couch is dead. It, it's no longer being developed on it. All that work has gone back into a branch of CouchDB, which we call the Nebraska Merge branch.
Okay.
Because we took our best engineers, took them offline for a week, sent them to one of the engineers' homes in Omaha, I think, Paul Davis' house.
Right.
And then they just, heads down, and there's a great blog post where you can follow, I don't know how many commits it was, 500 to 1,000 commits. Wow. They just, they just cranked away. They got it back to a point where it's like, okay, here's something we can give back to the community. Now the Apache review process begins, but the hope-- So it's a serious commitment to, to the community. Serious commitment, yeah. And so the hope is that when CouchDB 2. 0, or if we can do it around that time, comes out, then CouchDB will finally have a, a fully horizontally clustered story around it. Mm-hmm. So that kind of goes back to my initial point, like, the Postgres style. We tried to do it deliberately.
And, and, you know, let the community kind of, you know, we can say, okay, here, here it is. You know, um, sit back, take a poke at it, um, see if it stands up. And, you know, hopefully the community will accept that as a very good thing. So if, if I'm looking at, uh, evaluating a database, I'm looking at all the community options out there. I'm looking at, uh, Couch. I'm looking at Mongo. I'm looking at, uh, React. I'm looking, I'm just thinking of some of the, uh, ones that are here, uh, and are popular, or MySQL.
Uh, do you have any recommendations for how they can evaluate and, and look at, or get more information?
Yeah, um, I think what we try to do is understand what the needs are from the application perspective. Um, and so the things that we look for are, like, scale, uh, predictability, um, in production, which is a big one, I think, if you look at, you know, systems that peg things in memory and, and require that versus systems that are really built to be all disk from the beginning.
Um, and then the, the really big thing is, is there a distributed nature to this?
You know, um, the CouchDB model, um, that we're really, the reason we, we really love that model is there's no global write master.
Right.
That's like a huge, that's, that's like saying the speed of light. Well, I said right as if I really understood what that implication was. This is just like, let's step back.
Like, I'm, I'm a physicist, right?
Um, like, you know, Einstein was awesome because it'd be like, here's this thing we always thought was true. And it turns out it's not.
Okay. And because of that, we can do amazing things, right?
I can launch satellites. I can do GPS. I can, you know, I can build particle accelerators. All of this is true because, you know, nothing can go faster than the speed of light. And that means time's not constant. That was his big thing. Oh, time's not constant.
Right.
And so in this case, I think, um, developers are so used to assuming they have a, have to have a global write master.
Okay.
Um, but in this disconnected world of mobile devices that are everywhere and like you and I travel around the globe, right?
Why do my applications always have to call back to like North Virginia?
Like, okay, that's ridiculous.
So, so why can't my phone be the global room?
Can be, you know, the place where I write information now and then I can synchronize that later.
Right. Okay.
And so that is the number one thing that should take you to CouchDB. It is the only database that ships with the mobile strategy. So it gets you away from that. I have to have this canonical, this is, this is the, all that database of record stuff. Three-tier stack. I know exactly how to do this. I've done this for 30 years. Yeah, exactly. Um, it's, and in that sense, it's revolutionary. And I think it will take a long time for developers to fully understand the power of that. And that's something that we're trying to help kind of evangelize now. Um, but once you release that constraint, it's incredibly freeing and you can do some incredible, uh, things with it.
Is CouchDB something that, uh, uh, developers can, can really look at and contribute back to?
Is there, is there, are there opportunities maybe to somebody who's not a data scientist to be able to contribute to Couch? Yeah, absolutely. Um, you don't have to, you don't even have to, to be able to code. Um, so the community is very welcoming and that's one of the things we really, uh, we really loved about it when we were first looking at kind of API tiers that we could, you know, start to leverage to build this database as a service. Um, and the, the community continues to be vibrant. There's a great post, um, by, you know, by Noah Slater, thanking CouchDB. And he doesn't even, I don't, uh, apologies to Noah if he watches and I get this wrong. Um, because I haven't met him in person.
Right.
We've corresponded a lot, you know, through the community.
Um, I don't think he even pushes Erlang code, right?
Um, so you can jump in with documentation. You can jump in with, um, you know, being a part of the community, just answering questions about how to use it on email lists. Um, and there's, I think, a real, now you can always write Erlang code if you want to, or now JavaScript, or, you know, grab some portion of that and run with it or be a part of the build process or, or QA. But the community is very welcoming. Um, I can't think of somebody that wanted to contribute and wasn't accepted into the community at one level or another. And then they're very deliberate. People don't immediately become committers, but like, for instance, Russell Branca, a cloud employee, after being a friend of the community long before he started at cloud, and, you know, just became an Apache committer and started, you know, pushing patches. So, it's deliberate.
Right.
And that's, that's, again, it's, it's, it's slow to, to, you know, consider things that people put forward. And that, and that's actually another thing you mentioned that it's an Apache project. It's not, oh, this is an open source thing that's kind of out there. This is underneath the Apache umbrella.
Yeah.
And, and that's been big.
So, the, the, you know, the project has already survived the loss of its founder, right? Yeah.
So Damien Katz did an incredible job with the vision, uh, for, for this, you know, for this database, got it into Apache, um, and then, you know, through various, um, twists of fate, ended up, you know, having to leave the project, um, and, and do something else. Um, and, and, you know, there was a lot of worry that the project would die, but that's exactly what Apache, right, brings.
Yeah.
They, they, they gave it a, a, a, a foundation, a community, like a pre-baked community.
We're bringing it, it's stable, it's not going anywhere. And the community's big enough and strong enough to survive that, which, you know, sure, it's a dip and a hit, um, but now it's really, um, not just on the rebound, but it's starting to, to thrive again in terms of the number of commits and the amount of activity in the community. And, you know, speaking also of Damien, I remember, and I might be misremembering, but I could have swore there was an article that he had written where he kind of criticized his original work with couch.
Yeah.
And the now infamous blog post.
How, how does that, um, impact what, I mean, is, is he talking about the original couch implementation, but it's, it's changed since now or?
Yeah.
I should try to be a little diplomatic since we're on camera. I can give you a different answer over beers, I guess. Um, but first and foremost, I mean, uh, Damien deserves a lot of credit for creating this community and it, it has a lasting, his impression, you know, his, um, his legacy is that it's open and accepting. Um, and I think that's great, um, through business pressures, I think, um, you know, uh, he ended up, um, taking, you know, a lot of his ideas and re-implementing them into a different system.
Okay.
So they, he's really transitioned from the CouchDB community and into the memcached community.
Um, a particularly confusing point is that even though it doesn't speak the CouchDB interface, that new company and product has the word Couch in the name. Oh. Um, but it doesn't even speak CouchDB. So it's taken a lot of the ideas and, and kind of, um, um, wedged them, wedged them into, into memcached in a clustered style. But it's a second, second product kind of scenario. It's a second product, yeah. Um, and it's not to say that it's a terrible product. It's a good product for certain use cases. And if you're in like advertising or something like that, like ad serving, I think that's a, it's, it's a great product. But it serves a different purpose in its current form.
Okay.
Um, it's been confusing to the community and this is a place where I wish Apache would have been a little more, um, a little more draconian in their protection of brand and trademark than they were. But you know, the community survives it. Well, is there any last, um, as we're wrapping up here, is there any advice you would give to somebody directly, okay, I'm going to, I'm going to use Couch. Do you, should they come to Cloudant or should they look at the, uh, so is, is the common one more like very specific, like you have a use case and you already know what you should do, but maybe brew install CouchDB is good enough for the beginner who's just, yeah, it's a clear, clear distinction. So with Cloudant, we try to be, so we're, we're continuing to stretch the product in a way that Apache project can't just because of the time skills. So if you come to Cloudant, you get full text indexing and search, you get geospatial and we'll continue to expand that product and then contribute those things back in a way to, to the Apache projects, you know, so that they can be taken up at a time scale that's appropriate for Apache. Um, but the distinction is very clear. Um, if, you know, you want database as a service, which I think is the future, I think a decade from now, nobody will run their own databases.
We don't build our own power plants anymore. We pay for electrons on the wire. Right, right.
Right.
For a reason. But if I just want to get in, but exactly, get used to it. If you need to run it yourself or you just want to play with it, yes, Apache CouchDB is the way to go. And in its current state, it doesn't give you the ability to scale horizontally by just adding machines.
And we think that's critical to you being able to test whether or not this is the right choice. And so that's why we're making sure the project goes in that direction. But just for getting my feel for it. You know, yeah, I would say it's easiest to come in and sign up to Cloudant. Um, but you know, if you're sitting behind a firewall, um, or you just want to play with it on your laptop and you're offline, you should always have the ability to play with it offline. Right, right. Um, you know, with your Mac, go and grab the CouchDB application, drag it to your apps folder and double click it in your live. There's nothing to do. Oh, okay. There's just a regular app. You don't even have to do it. Yeah, couchdb. org downloads. Oh, couchdb. org. All right.
Well, thank you very much for taking the time to time to sit down with me. Pleasure. Thank you. Appreciate it. Okay, that's fine. Bye.